So here's a question that people commonly ask:\h
"Why is stream entry called the right view,
and why can a change of view be so special that it\h
becomes actually liberating? Don't most Buddhists
already have right view in the sense that their\h
views are in line with the Buddhist teaching?"
Well, the thing is that, as the suttas say,
there are two factors to the
arising of the right view. So on a mundane\h
level, all you need to change your view about a
topic is the utterance of another. You just need\h
to get information and then you just change
your mind about, I don't know, politics or\h
something. But when it comes to the dhamma,
there's that second factor there that is also\h
essential for that change of view to occur, which
is yoniso manasikāra. So then basically it's not a change\h
of view on that kind of arms length level where I
just exchange one bit of information that I agree\h
with for another bit of information which, as you\hsaid,
that's pretty much most people's\h
relationship with the Buddhist teaching;
it's just agreeing with a different information than\h
they had before. But this is like, yoniso manasikāra being,
as some other suttas describe it, it's inseparable\h
from seeing your own mind, seeing the signs of your\hown mind.
So when you take the Buddhist teaching\h
in its most condensed form, which is suffering,
the origin of suffering, the escape from suffering,\h
and the path to the escape from suffering,
you would realize that if you don't see your\h
own mind, any information that you might have
about this, how will it possibly be personal?
How will it possibly be relevant to you in
your own situation? As the suttas say, the dhamma\h
has to be realized by the wise for themselves.
So if there isn't that kind of ability to\h
even see where this stuff is supposed to apply,
you can have all the information you want, but\h
your view about where suffering comes from will
still be conditioned by the extent of awareness of\h
your own mind that you still have, which for most
people is basically zero. So you will not be able\h
to clearly see what craving is for example.
You might have all sorts of ideas about it, but those\h
ideas will necessarily be wrong if you haven't
developed that internal room or space let's say\h
to see where the craving actually arises on the
right level. And what is that space? Well, it's\h
again, anything you might say is just going to be
more information; it's what gets revealed on its\h
own provided you make the right effort.
Towards what? Towards virtue, sense restraint, not letting\h
yourself spill out towards external objects that
will obscure your mind even more. So it's not\h
that these things will inherently reveal your
mind, because you can be keeping the precepts\h
and restraining your senses for all sorts of
wrong reasons and many people do that today with\h
no insight coming from it whatsoever, but it's
a indispensable prerequisite for you to be able\h
to see where your mind actually is. So, it's kind
of like, you know, you have to remove\h
the stuff that's in the way.
Like there's a whole tree that fell on the way that you\h
have to walk. So, it's not that removing the tree
in and of itself puts you at your destination, but\h
if the tree is there, you will not be able to walk\hthrough.
So that's why, as the Buddha\h
said, virtue is not the dhamma, but there is no
dhamma without virtue. So if you develop these\h
prerequisites, what will you start to see?
Well, in the process of even developing them, you\h
will come to see that there is this
separate dimension; not that it didn't exist\h
before, but that you always overlooked.
You were always either landing too much on the side\h
of the sense objects and sight, sounds, smells,
taste, touches, or kind of like semi-mystical\h
grandiose ideas about how everything works and
explanatory concepts and motions\h
to kind of help yourself deal with the pressure of
sight, sounds, smells, tastes, and touches.
So those are\hthe two dimensions that a person
would know. And then what's there kind of neither\h
in one nor the other? It's the citta.
It's that attitude at the root level\h
of your experience that you cannot directly see,
you can only indirectly know. You have this kind\h
of agitation, obsession; one day it's there,
one day it's not there, the other day it's kind\h
of revolving around this types of thoughts,
the other day a different types of thoughts.
And so it's that kind of
ambiguous, indirect nature of the mind that\h
the only way to reveal it is by ceasing to
let yourself spill out into sense objects. And\h
then the other prerequisite, as the Buddha said, is
to not delight in company, even if you're\h
keeping the precepts, because then that will
do the opposite; that will keep spilling\h
you out into the world, into resolving
things on the level of getting people to\h
agree with you, to not disapprove of you,
to do things as a group. And all of\h
that is actually obscuring that internal, fully
individual and personal dimension of where your\h
own craving actually arises.
Because you take "external" now as a starting point again.\h
So you would be attending to the wrong signs
and features, namely what do other people think of\h
me?, how do they look? and so on. Whereas all of that
actually means nothing compared to the real signs\h
and features, which cannot be seen
on the outside. It's your own privileged position\h
in relation to your own mind.
Yes, and also, it's not that other people
inherently make you
take the external standpoint. It's that you\h
already start with the external standpoint.
So then other people will just keep reinforcing\h
that. If you don't keep it in check
and especially if you keep seeking it out, which is\h
the problem. It's not that you have to avoid other
people and run away from them. It's if you delight\h
in company. In other words, if you use that as
as a thing to kind of keep yourself afloat when\h
you're bored or something. Well, that's a perfect\hexample:
if you were not to seek company\h
as a means of enjoyment and pleasure, what would
you be forced to encounter and face? It's that\h
full extent of your mind's pressure towards this.
And then you would in the position
to unravel what's actually happening,
why is it that this is painful,\h
not to have this company? Why?
That could manifest as a sense of loneliness\h
for example. Exactly. But then, you know,
it doesn't need to come to the point of you having\h
the view that other people is how you resolve your
suffering, that other people are the escape from\h
suffering. Because, again, it's not the view
on the level of external information that you\h
just pick and change at will.
If you're not aware of where the craving is, on the\h
right level, in your own experience, whether you
like it or not, you place the blame for the\h
suffering where it isn't. That will be inevitable.
Yes. So then doesn't matter whether you blame the\h
fact that you're lonely or you blame the fact on that
I'm not free from X fetter, which is why this is\h
still here. Or, you know, it's because I was
born like this, or my upbringing was like that, or\h
because yesterday I did this unwholesome thing.
But no. The thing is, as the Buddha said,
the dhamma is timeless. So it's right here and now.
It's the attitude that you have towards what\h
has arisen right here and now. That's where the
problem is, and that's what you would become able\h
to see if you have removed all these obstructions
of your behavior and then you're basically, as\h
he would say, delving with the knife to uncover
Where is that craving? Where does it arise, and to\h
what extent is this... what level of input do
I have in it? Because it's not that it's there on its own,
that you're fully subjected to it;
you're maintaining it. And you also have to get to\h
understand what it is that maintains it, which is
what the Buddha would call the unwholesome\hactions.
That's where you would develop that completely universal\h
and incapable of being doubted standard of what is
beneficial and what is unbeneficial. Because now\h
you have dug up that thing that was there all\halong,
but because you were so distracted\h
by other things that felt much more natural,
you didn't see it and you didn't take it as your\h
actual reference point. But now that you see it,
it becomes completely obvious that anything else\h
except this cannot be a right guidance for
wholesome and unwholesome. That's not where the\h
origin of suffering is. No. So any emphasizing
anything else will be hit or miss, will be kind\h
of depending on the day, depending on the weather,
depending on the hour of the day, maybe it\h
will have an influence of this internal animal,
the citta, maybe it won't. Maybe it will make it\h
worse. And that's what most people's practice of
the Buddhist teaching revolves around.\h
It's pretty much like, probabilistically they might
be able to escape the suffering or not. But\h
yes, if you see that on the right level,
see the citta, see that indirect attitude, you could\h
call it the root attitude that's being exhibited
towards sights, sounds, smells, taste, touches,\h
even thoughts, no matter how lofty, how kind of
grandiose and important and even thoughts\h
about dhamma, like the most justified things that
might come up. Well, the attitude behind that\h
is where the citta is, and your view of
what is wholesome and unwholesome would be
in\hrelation to that attitude. So the attitude needs
purification. Yes. So then you would realize\h
in that sense there is no right object.
There's no right kind of thing that you can land on\h
without questioning your attitude behind it.
Yes. Just as sensuality is a man's intention.\h
That's the same principle.
Yes, so greed, aversion, and delusion is your intention\h
completely. So then if you think that you can pick
a safe kind of pasture where you do not
have to question your motivation for
being there and letting your attention\h
land there, that means you completely are not
seeing the reference point, because the reference\h
point would be: Why? Why am I allowing my attention
to land on this sight, sound, smell, taste, touch\h
or even mental image, as complex and and intricate
as it might be, there's always this peripheral\h
attitude in regard to that thing where you would
have the passionate obsession, the doubt, the\h
the kind of obsessive doubt, that just keeps
kind of revolving around the thing, even though\h
you already know the answer, but it just
wants that emotional gratification out of it. You\h
have all the five hindrances basically on that
peripheral level that you absolutely will not see\h
for as long as you think that the object itself
is the measure of wholesome and unwholesome.\h
Yes. And that is why the sense restraint is so
important, because you are restraining dwelling way\h
too much on the external object, so to speak.
Which also means that as long as this is not understood\h
nowhere in the world are you safe.
You will be basically everywhere, even if you\h
go in a spaceship to another planet, you will
still be a prey to suffering there. But also, once\h
this is seen, that safety cannot leave you.
So wherever you go in the "external world", you'll\h
be safe because it is that relationship between
you and your own mind that is the determining\h
factor here. Yes.
And you would see it in the suttas when the Buddha\h
would say: Whatever form, whether past, present
or future, big or small, inferior or superior,
it's in regard to all form that this attitude
has to be developed. In other words, the attitude\h
of dispassion, the attitude of non-ownership.
So then for somebody who doesn't see their own
mind\hclearly, whether they like it or not, they will be
maintaining attitudes of passion in regard to some\h
form, some feeling, some perception, some intention
some consciousness. So it's in regard to that\h
kind of... it's the most comprehensive scope where
nothing is left out, even as that suttas says: If you were\h
to perceive "nibbāna" and then because of thinking
that that itself is the purity, overlooking your\h
attitude in regard to it, for that reason alone
you wouldn't actually realize nibbāna. You would\h
be delighting and maintaining your existence,
your being, your bhava, through that, because\h
it's not about the object, not even about the
experience and the the kind of content of it,
it's about: How is the animal relating to it?
Yes. So on paper, somebody could come up with a\h
quite accurate description of what nibbāna is,
but their background attitude towards it could still\h
be wrong, which means that it's not actually now
the nibbāna. And even when they have it in their\h
own experience so to speak, through the
universally correct development of virtue,
sense-restraint, renunciation, without which you will
not even get to the point where you\h
could make that mistake, because you will not have
realized the phenomenon of dispassion.
There, in regard to that...
Let's say you have a well established attitude of not
inclining\htowards sensuality, of being dispassionate towards
the world, recognizing the impermanence\h
of life and the uselessness of clinging to\hit,
as many ascetics in the Buddha's time were\h
able to do, if you read some of those stories.
But then in regard to that phenomenon, of what\h
they think is a pure mind, which compared to the
average person factually would be, well,
they don't\hsee their attitude in regard to that.
They don't see to what extent they are dependent on that,
to\hwhat extent they are taking that for granted and
taking refuge in that. And then for that reason\h
alone, what they think is the root problem would
be on the level of: not having this great\h
development – phenomenon – of dispassion that
I have brought about. But that still fails to\h
arrive at the level where the problem is:
Even in regard to this, what is my attitude?\h
But obviously that doesn't mean that you need
to necessarily get to that level and then\h
kind of correct course. No, it's like,
it's everywhere. It's now in regard to whatever\h
you're seeing, hearing, tasting, smelling,
touching, thinking. There is some attitude there\h
that's kind of like, you could say it's independent
of you, but you're certainly responsible for\h
steering it further in certain directions.
So it's neither fully yours nor\h
is it completely out of your control.
And with the right view, where the line is will be
clearly\hseen and beyond doubt. Exactly. Yes.
You will see what is the extent of your input,
which\his why you would then be free from any wavering
and doubt in regard to what the practice\h
is and all these considerations like:
"How long is it going to take?" and "Who came\h
up with this?" and "Where is this going to lead\hme?"
Even if those doubts arise, again\hbecause you see
the attitude in regard to whatever arises now,
you wouldn't fall for it, and that's\hwhy the Buddha said,
the mind that with ayoniso manasikāra, they would be
inevitably to some extent revolving around\h
questions of Who was I? Where did I come from?
What am I right now? Where will I become later?\h
Because you realize, even through the Buddhist\hteaching
you could be feeding those views.
You could be using the pronouncements about X or Y
that the Buddha made, to revolve around your own\h
doubts of trying to explain things.
Thinking that somehow figuring things out will\h
resolve your suffering. Again, overlooking
"Well, what is my attitude in regard to all this doubting\h
and clarifying?" and you know, trying to get the\hanswers.
Is it an attitude of dispassion? Well,\h
realistically, most of the time it's not.
And seeing now the mind, which depends on\h
virtue and also seclusion you mentioned, that
doesn't actually now require explanation.
There's no causal [relation] like, first this, then that,
and so on, and then at at some point\h
the mind will come along. It's not like that.
So there is a difference between explaining things,\h
how one thing results in another, and an accurate
description of, let's say, where the mind is\h
to be found, or what we often call 'right level'.
So it might be useful for people to also\h
recognize that explanations are one kind of talk,
but that's not what we're doing here. It is more\h
like what is necessary in order to recognize the mind,
which is already there, and that is not the\h
product of an explanation. It's more a quality of
the utterance of another being the right\h
description, but... that it points you to find it.
Yes. And then it depends on the listener\h
how far they take that description "inwards",
so that they actually see what is being\hdescribed.
Well, the origin, like the yoniso, meaning
the origin, like in the sense of, it being
the womb that kind of hovers over this whole\hthing.
This attitude that hovers over this\h
entire thing, that underlies it, that contains it.
And then, that's where the mind is. And that's where\h
you would be either – through your carelessness –
making it worse, when it's already in an unwholesome\h
state, or as wild as it might have gotten, if you
understood where it is, you would be able\h
to, first of all, see it as such; not lose
perspective in regard to that, as the satipaṭṭhāna sutta says,
even where your mind is lustful, you know:
the mind is lustful, and then you would be fully\h
capable of bringing it out of that state,
without having to wish and hope on random methods and\h
practices that worked in the past, and having to
combine them and mix them and make new ones
or something, hoping that it will work again.
It's like, if that's your level of\hpractice,
then it's not much better than depending on the weather.
If\hyou have understood your mind, you should be able to
abandon any unwholesome state. On the spot.\h
Yes. Well, not necessarily on the spot, but
be beyond doubt about what has to be done in
order to abandon it. Because as the Buddha said,
it's a matter of feeding; you feed the\h
hindrances and you starve the hindrances.
Yes, which means that when you see your mind, in a sense,\h
that's also it. Yes. Because with that
will now come the knowledge how it's fed, right?\h
Yes. But even then, it wouldn't be like...\h
basically, it's a certainty that you know\h
what to do. You still have to do it. If you...
Yes, but the doing is to now\hnot feed...
Yes. So then if
having seen your mind, you\hneed another step,
that's because you don't see your mind.
That's what I meant now by on the spot...
So\hthere's an immediacy to it. Yes. Exactly.
Because, you know, somebody could fall\h
into that view like: "Oh yes, I do see my mind"
and then I start doing XYZ, and it's like:
Well,\hif you feel that that's required, you should be
cautious about whether you actually see your\h
mind or not. Because as the Buddha said,
it's through avijjā, that's the root\h
cause of the source of the\hwhole river.
So if you have actually undone your\havijjā,
that should be able to fix the problem in and of itself.
Yes. So we can say that ignorance,\h
avijjā, is in relation to the mind. Not knowing or
ignoring mind, is the problem of all this.
Yes. Because it's an either/or. You can't
be ignoring the mind and then going towards\h
the direction of wholesome; you can't be
seeing the mind and then still acting out of\h
greed, aversion and delusion. That's impossible.